Chapter 7 – Reduced Sounds Unstressed words have reduced vowels. The Downside of
Intonation Reduced sounds are all those extra sounds created by an absence of lip,
tongue, jaw, and throat movement. They're a principal function of intonation and are
truly indicative of the American sound. Reduced sounds are valleys. American
intonation is made up of peaks and valleys, tops of staircases, and bottoms
of staircases. To have strong peaks, you'll have to develop deep valleys. These
deep valleys should be filled with all kinds of reduced vowels, one in
particular, the completely neutral schwa. Ignore spelling. Since you probably first
became acquainted with English through the printed word, this is going to be quite a
challenge. The position of a syllable is more important than spelling as an
indication of correct pronunciation. For example, the words photograph and
photography each have two O's and an A. The first word is stressed on the first
syllable, so photograph sounds like photograph. The second word is stressed on
the second syllable, photography, so the word comes out photography. You can see
here that their spelling doesn't tell you how they sound. Word stress or intonation
will determine the pronunciation. Listening to words. Concentrate on hearing
the pure sounds, not trying to make the word fit a familiar spelling. Otherwise,
you'll be taking the long way around and giving yourself both a lot of extra work
and an accent. Syllables that are perched atop a peak or a staircase are strong
sounds. That is, they maintain their original pronunciation. On the other hand,
syllables that fall in the valleys or on a lower stair step are weak sounds, thus
they're reduced. Some vowels are reduced completely to schwas, a very relaxed
sound, while others are only toned down. In the following exercises, we'll be
dealing with these toned-down sounds. In the introduction, read this first page IV,
I talked about overpronouncing. This section will handle that
overpronunciation. You're going to skim over words, you're going to through
certain sounds. Your peaks are going to be quite strong, but your valleys blurry. A
very intuitive aspect of intonation that this practice will help you develop.
Articles such as the, uh, are usually very reduced sounds. Before a consonant, the
and uh are both schwa sounds, which are reduced. Before a vowel, however, you'll
notice a change. The schwa of the turns into a long e plus a Y. The book changes
to thee only book. A hat becomes an ugly hat. The article a becomes an. Think of an
orange rather than an orange. An opening, an eye, an imaginary animal.